[
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "AN AQUEOUS SOLUTION IS ACIDIC IF",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "its pH value is high",
            "it s corrosive",
            "it changes the colour of litmus",
            "it has a bitter taste",
            "it contains more H<sub>3</sub>O- than OH-"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The following oxides react with water except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Na<sub>2</sub>O",
            "SO<sub>3</sub>",
            "NO<sub>2</sub>",
            "CO<sub>2</sub>",
            "CuO"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a property of trioxonitrate (V) salts?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Positive reaction to the brown ring test",
            "Ability to dissolve in cold water",
            "Decomposition on being strongly heated",
            "Production of effervescence with saturated Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>solution",
            "Evolution of gas with concentrated H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>and copper turnings"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following methods is suitable for the preparation of an insoluble salt?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Action of an acid on a metal",
            "Double decomposition",
            "Neutralisation",
            "Action of an acid on a trioxocarbonate (IV)",
            "Action of an acid on an oxide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "What is the function of sulphur (IV) oxide in the reaction represented by the following equation? SO<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>S<sub>(g)</sub>→ 3S<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Dehydrating agent",
            "Oxidising agent",
            "Bleaching agent",
            "Acid",
            "Precipitant"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following will produce oxygen and hydrogen during its electrolysis using platinum electrode?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Glucose solution",
            "Aqueous copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (IV)",
            "Dilute sodium chloride solution",
            "Concentrated hydrochloric acid",
            "Dilute copper (ll) chloride solution"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "What mass of copper would be deposited by a current of 1. 0 ampere passing for 965 seconds through copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (IV) solution? [Cu = 63.5; 1F = 96500C]",
        "explanation": "Cu<sup>2+</sup>+ 2e- → Cu, From the equation 2 Faraday will liberate 63.5gm of copper The quantity of electricity passed (Q) Q = 1. 0 965 = 965 coulomb :. 2 x 96500 → 63.5, 965 → x. x =<sup>965</sup>/<sub>2x96500</sub>x 63.5 = 0.3175g \\(\\approx\\) 0.328",
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "0.318g",
            "0.635g",
            "18g",
            "6.35g",
            "9.65g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "How many electrons are removed from Cr<sup>2-</sup>when it is oxidized to CrO<sub>4</sub><sup>2-</sup>?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "o",
            "2",
            "4",
            "8",
            "10"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Substances which absorb water from the atmosphere without dissolving in it are sid to be",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "anhydrous",
            "hygroscopic",
            "insolube",
            "hydrated",
            "efflorescent"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Pipe-borne water is usually chlorinated in order to",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "improve the teste of the water",
            "remove the hardness in the water clear",
            "coagulate sediments in the water",
            "kill harmful bacteria in the water",
            "make the water clear and colourless"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following can be added to dissolve the precipitate formed in the reaction represented by the following equation? CaCl<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>C<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4(s)</sub>⇌ CaC<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Calcium chloride solution",
            "Concentrated hydrochloric acid",
            "Ethanol",
            "Ethanedioc acid",
            "Aqueous ammonia"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The spontaneity of a chemical reaction is determined by the change in the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "concentration of the reactants",
            "temperature of the system",
            "free energy of the system",
            "pressure applied to the system",
            "volume of the reactants"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Two metallic ions commonly present in hard water are",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Ca<sup>2+</sup>and Zn<sup>2+</sup>",
            "Cu<sup>2+</sup>and Na<sup>+</sup>",
            "Mg<sup>2+</sup>and Ca<sup>2+</sup>",
            "Fe<sup>2+</sup>and Na<sup>+</sup>",
            "Zn<sup>2+</sup>and Cu<sup>2+</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Rusting of iron is an example of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "deliquescence",
            "decomposition",
            "displacement reaction",
            "redox reaction",
            "reversible reaction"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Aluminium is extracted from",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "magnetite",
            "cryolite",
            "bauxite",
            "cassiterite"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Metals are said to be malleable because they",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "are good conductors heat",
            "are good conductors of electricity",
            "can be beaten into sheets",
            "can be alloyed",
            "can be polished"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "A device used in the laboratory for intermittent production of gases without heating is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Leibing condenser",
            "aspirator",
            "delivery tube",
            "inverted funnel",
            "Kipp's apparatus"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following can undergo both addition reactions and substitution reactions?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Benzene",
            "Pentane",
            "Propene",
            "Hexane",
            "Ethene"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The liquid product of the destructive distillation of coal is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "kerosene",
            "ethanol",
            "ammoniacal liquor",
            "paraffin oil",
            "aqueous ammonia"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following alkanes has the highest boiling point?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "pentane",
            "ethane",
            "propane",
            "butana",
            "hexane"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Petrol consists mainly of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "polymers",
            "alkanoates",
            "hydrocarbons",
            "alktanols",
            "alkenes"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Dehydration of ethanol produces",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "ethanoic acid",
            "propan-1,2,3-triol",
            "ethene",
            "ethanal",
            "methanol"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "When alkanols react with sodium, the ga evolved is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "hydrogen",
            "oxygen",
            "methane",
            "ethyne",
            "carbon (IV) oxide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The products of the reaction between CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH and CH<sub>3</sub>OH are H<sub>2</sub><br>O and",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOCH<sub>3</sub>",
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOCH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>",
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COOH",
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH",
            "CH<sub>3</sub>COOH"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "A positive reaction to Fehling's test indicates the presence of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "strach",
            "reducing sugars",
            "oxidizing agents",
            "alkanoic acids",
            "alkanols"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following compounds is used as a gaseous fuel?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "CH<sub>3</sub>-COO-CH<sub>2-</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>",
            "CH<sub>3-</sub>CH<sub>2-</sub>CH<sub>2-</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>",
            "CHCI<sub>3</sub>",
            "CH<sub>3-</sub>CH<sub>2-</sub>COOH",
            "CH<sub>3-</sub>C=CH"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]